<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-08-03T06:24:36+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jared Tulayan</title><subtitle>Rutgers Computer Science student</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Luthery Log 4: Milling Mistakes</title><link href="/blog/luther4.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Luthery Log 4: Milling Mistakes" /><published>2022-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-08-03T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/luther4</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/luther4.html"><![CDATA[<p>I got busy over the past couple of days, so this log will cover the past couple of days of work.</p>

<p>First day was spent routing out the body. I got around to making a template in CAD, then using the CNC to cut it out onto 3/4” plywood.
I needed it thick enough so that the pattern bearing for the 1/4” bit could run along it. It seemed to work well, though I accidentally
milled a little too deep for the last pickup cavity as well as the neck pocket. The pockets all seem to be a little too small to take in
their respective parts, but that should be fine with a little bit of sanding/post-process.</p>

<figure style="width: 50%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-08-03/template.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 120%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
</figure>

<p>At the time of routing these out, I had to wait for some parts to test fit the rest of them, so in the meanwhile, I began milling the guitar neck.</p>

<p>The milling process for the neck is as follows:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Rout out the tuner holes (and screw holes if applicable, but I didn’t have tuners to design in)</li>
  <li>Carve the back neck profile</li>
  <li>Mill out the truss rod slot, insert truss rod and glue on fretboard</li>
  <li>Rout the inlay</li>
  <li>Cut the fret slots</li>
  <li>Carve the fretboard radius and other neck features</li>
  <li>Cut out the neck</li>
</ol>

<p>I only had time for steps 1 and 2 this night. I ran the roughing job while I was routing the neck plane pockets, and watched the finishing pass.
My first mistake was not adding enough padding past the neck in the roughing pass. This caused some issues with the finishing pass, particularly when it
moved up to pass over the heel; because it was actually cutting into material since there was no padding, it ended up pulling the bit down and out of the
collet. This trend seemed to keep up into the next day.</p>

<figure style="width: 75%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-08-03/mill-mistake.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 80%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">You can see at the top of the heel and the bottom of the headstock where the router milled into</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>With some scrap, I just filled in the milled parts. Hopefully the parts aren’t too conspicuous.</p>

<figure style="width: 75%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-08-03/mill-fix.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 120%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
</figure>

<p>The next day I had my Tune-o-matic parts on me, so I used them to test fit the holes and placements of them.</p>

<figure style="width: 50%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-08-03/testfit.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 120%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
</figure>

<p>These looked in place, so I went ahead and drilled the holes using a 29/64” (~0.4531” or ~11.5mm) brad-point drill bit.
I tried to tilt the drill bit forward for the hardtail holes to make the hardtail lay “flat”, which may have thrown the hardtail slightly off alignment.</p>

<figure style="width: 50%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-08-03/rout.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 120%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
</figure>

<p>Finishing up, I managed to clean up the backside enough to get it onto the CNC and rout out the truss rod. The rod doesn’t fit in yet;
it needs some adjustment to get it in, but it is 90% of the way there.</p>

<figure style="width: 50%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-08-03/truss.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 80%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
</figure>

<p>I still need to make an adapter plate for our binding router jig so that we can use our DeWalt router with it, as well as create the inlay designs
to mill out both the negatives and the actual inlay pieces. Even with all that, the end draws near. I’m very excited to see what this guitar will
look like when it’s done.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="art" /><category term="woodworking" /><category term="guitar" /><category term="makerspace" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Luthery Log 3: Starcaster Body Gets Put Together</title><link href="/blog/luther3.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Luthery Log 3: Starcaster Body Gets Put Together" /><published>2022-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-27T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/luther3</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/luther3.html"><![CDATA[<p>Finishing up the assembly of this body today.</p>

<p>I got the bottom machined out, and luckily it was only a minor cleanup job to get it to look as good as the top.
There isn’t really anything else past that; I guess I worried for nothing. The thickness didn’t even seem to be an issue;
it was really just a thickness issue in one corner of the bottom, so no issues there.</p>

<p>I ended up choosing Telecaster Thinline f-holes to put on the Starcaster. In my head I thought that the only way to get these cut out right would be by hand,
so that you can make the sides of the cutout be perpendicular to the curvature of the top carve. I used a drill to hog out some material to put a coping saw blade through,
and just went to work. Smoothing the edges was done using a large flat file, and a round rasp, then finishing using some 80 grit sandpaper and some small files. The holes aren’t
perfect, but they look pretty good to me.</p>

<figure style="width: 50%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-27/tops.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 75%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
</figure>

<p>Gluing up was done all in one job, regrettably. In retrospect I could’ve gotten away with gluing down the bottom first, then the top after the bottom cures, but I decided to try and
do both at the same time since I was impatient. I aimed to minimize squeeze-out in the body since cleaning the inside of glue would be a hard challenge, but I may have added too much to the centerblock. 
Conversely, the amount I added to the sides for glue might’ve actually been not enough, since those areas had basically no squeeze out. I think if I were to redo this (which I might need to),
I would have just applied glue to one mating surface instead of both, since applying to both took too much time, allowing the glue to dry before working it.</p>

<p>I used whatever clamps I could: I tried to use as many wooden screw clamps as I could fit since those were the least likely to damage the top and bottom, 
but had to grab some other plastic clamps and some E-Z Grip clamps. I’m worried that the amount of time putting down glue and spreading it caused alot of it to dry up
prematurely, but the majority of it seemed wet and workable when I put the body together. Luckily, any glue-up seams will be covered up with binding, so hopefully those edges are pretty protected.</p>

<figure style="width: 50%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-27/glueup.png') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 100%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
</figure>

<p>With the body done, I’m going to need to figure out how to use the routing channel jig that we have laying in storage. I had a carrier from LMII ordered so that the body can be held
square with the table during routing, but I still don’t really know how to use that, much less in conjunction with our routing jig.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="art" /><category term="woodworking" /><category term="guitar" /><category term="makerspace" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Luthery Log 2: Starcaster Build Goes Somewhat Wrong</title><link href="/blog/luther2.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Luthery Log 2: Starcaster Build Goes Somewhat Wrong" /><published>2022-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/luther2</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/luther2.html"><![CDATA[<p>Today I focused on getting the top and bottom carved out.</p>

<p>Unfortunately, things did not go quite as planned, but such is the way of life.</p>

<p>To start off with the good: I did carve the top, and it looks great.
The odd geometry of the model that I used to carve the top seems to not be too bad. 
I was able to sand it smooth pretty easily.</p>

<figure style="width: 100%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-26/finish.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 90%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">The top carve is very gentle, and the terrible gemoetry isn't so noticeable</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>The top mates well with the center, and the glue from yesterday set properly, so that crack is basically sealed.
I did notice that the guitar centerblock was a bit too thick, so I took it to the CNC to surface it down some.
This left the thickness of the top at ~1.35”, since the thickness of the top and bottom at their edges were ~0.4” total, and the total thickness
of the guitar needed to be 1.75” from top edge to bottom edge.</p>

<figure style="width: 50%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-26/centerblock.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 90%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">Surfacing the top. Luckily, it didn't crack on the way.</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>I did notice today that setting up the top for the topside carve that it wouldn’t adhere to the glue when I was gluing it down to the machine bed. Further inspection
made me realize that the top was cupping ever so slightly, so I had to apply body weight to actually get it to adhere.</p>

<figure style="width: 50%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-26/step.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 90%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">I'm actually standing on the machine bed to get this to glue down</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>Note this down? Because this becomes important later.</p>

<p>After machining the top, I didn’t want to make the same mistake of trying to chisel out the tabs, so I opted to hand cut them instead.
I started with a coping saw, but got impatient and cut it out with the bandsaw. I accidentally nicked the top a little bit while I was adjusting,
and almost had a heart attack. Luckily, the nick is minimal, and I will probably remove that material anyway making the binding channel,
so not much is lost.</p>

<p>While the bottom side was being carved on the CNC, I spent some time smoothing out the top and planning the f-holes. Something about it didn’t seem right
when I laid it out, so I chose to sleep on the thought. I might design my own f-holes to go on this guitar; may as well since I’ve mentally deviated from the
original idea of the p93 styling.</p>

<figure style="width: 50%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-26/f-holes.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 90%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">F-hole layout. Notice the nick on the guitar?</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>So remember the note about the top bowing? As it turns out, the blank I was using for the bottom was bowing as well. This, however, was bowing enough
that it actually overcame the adhesive; either I just didn’t press down hard enough when putting the piece down, or it just came undone due to the force.
This actually caused an inconsistency in the thickness of the top: <strong>at its lowest, it is half if not less than the thickness it’s supposed to be.</strong></p>

<figure style="width: 100%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-26/thickness.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 57%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">Left: original 5mm thickness<br />Right: the bowed up side...</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>This creates a couple of issues:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The finishing carve, which I didn’t do yet, will either not properly round off since it’s too low, or worse case, may mill right through the bottom since it’s bowing upwards.</li>
  <li>The thinness of the bottom might not leave me enough play room to sand and smooth.</li>
  <li>The acoustic integrity of the guitar <em>might</em> be compromised since it’s so thin in some regions.</li>
</ul>

<p>This leaves me with two options:</p>
<ol>
  <li>Make a new bottom</li>
  <li>Make do with this discrepancy</li>
</ol>

<p>Judging by the delta in change—about 2mm over the width of 381mm, so &gt; 0.005mm in height every 1mm along the width—I’m inclined to say I can make do with this top.
Only tomorrow will really tell if I can make do with this top. If it ends up cutting through, I’ll need to find more figured maple to make the bottom. 
If I do end up using this top, it should be generally unnoticeable that there is a height difference in the first place; it’s such a gentle difference that probably won’t be felt 
unless you’re looking for it.</p>

<p>Tomorrow’s goals are to try and get this glued up. I don’t have any spool clamps, and I don’t really want to wait for the materials to make them, so I’ll have to make do with another idea.
I’ll also need to buy some binding, and possibly some perfling. That’s for a later time.</p>

<p>That’s all for now. Hopefully I can right my wrongs tomorrow.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="art" /><category term="woodworking" /><category term="guitar" /><category term="makerspace" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Luthery Log 1: Starcaster Build</title><link href="/blog/luther1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Luthery Log 1: Starcaster Build" /><published>2022-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-25T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/luther1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/luther1.html"><![CDATA[<p>I have had this dream: to own some kind of semi-hollow guitar of my own making.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<figure style="width: 100%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-25/riviera.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 38%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">A wine red Epiphone Riviera P93</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>At first, it was going to be an Epiphone Riviera P93, partially because this dream started when I was
in high school: I was getting into The Strokes, and Nick Valensi’s P94 was something I’ve always wanted to own. 
However, it didn’t feel like my style, and so my dream settled on this wine red P93, with its beautiful gold hardware
and triple dogear P90 setup. Tonewise, it was bright and airy due to the single coil setup and semi-hollow body,
but the tone could also fatten up with the right settings. I found out recently Lucy Dacus also uses it, which
had further set this guitar as something of a dream to acquire.</p>

<p><br /></p>

<figure style="width: 100%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-25/starcaster.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 40%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">Fender's Modern Player Starcaster in Cherry Red Sunburst</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>However, I had also begun getting into Deep Sea Diver at the same time, and the lead guitarist Jessica Dobson always
rocked this cherry sunburst semi-hollow guitar that I had never seen the likes of before. Research had me find out that
it was a Fender Modern Player Starcaster, and my mind had fixated on this guitar as well. Something about the stylings of
a Fender in a semi-hollow guitar package was very alluring to me. The hardware wasn’t that eccentric; just two humbuckers
and a Tune-o-matic, but the tone and style was unique; I had never seen an offset body used for a semi-hollow,
nor had I seen the likes of a stepdown headstock. The tone was unique too: because the body was separate from neck, the 
transfer of energy  between the neck and the body was different as opposed to a set neck, creating a different tone. 
However, in the hands of people like Jessica Dobson, the tone could shift, change, transform into something more.
I fell in love with it when I saw it first used by her.</p>

<p>Somehow, I just never seemed to be able to settle on one, so in college, I planned to make a cross between the two:
a Fender Starcaster with the hardware and color of a P93. It is a major challenge: if you look online for any information
regarding this guitar, there is little to none; the guitar was largely unsuccessful, so Fender had stopped producing them
altogether. You can find Fender Starcasters used, but for extremely high prices. The next best thing was a Squier
Starcaster, but I’m not a fan of the Squier humbuckers, Besides, I was hoping to treat this project as my magnum opus,
my biggest project yet before I leave the Makerspace.</p>

<p>Today I started with machining out the centerblock, top, and bottom. According to some documents and forums I read online,
the starcaster is a sandwich, much like a Thinline Telecaster. Ideally the sides would be bent, but I haven’t been able
to get the tooling to make veneer, or the tooling to bend said veneer. Making a centerblock with the sides attached would
just be easier from a logistics standpoint.</p>

<figure style="width: 30%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-25/split.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 120%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">A split in the centerblock...</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>Machining the centerblock wasn’t hard; it’s a one sided job, and the body isn’t too thick. There were a couple things I found out:</p>
<ul>
  <li>The router was connected to a shared outlet. It tripped a breaker in the middle of the cut. That might’ve been from me, 2 years ago.</li>
  <li>The centerblock is super fragile! It split at some point after the machining. Luckily, the split was clean and easy to fix.</li>
</ul>

<p>After machining the centerblock, I had to machine the tops. Earlier, I had jointed a face by using a planer sled that allows me to move a piece
through the planer with shims. It yields a flatter result than surfacing it on the CNC, but only if you shim the piece properly.</p>

<figure style="width: 50%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-25/sled.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 120%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
</figure>

<p>I began to machine the underside of the top. I had used a 3D printer to print a top prototype prior to machining to get an idea of the topology, so I wasn’t going in completely blind.</p>

<figure style="width: 50%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-25/prototype.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 120%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
</figure>

<p>This was pretty good, though it took really long–about 30 minutes for both a roughing and finishing pass. For future cuts, I may just stick to only a finishing pass; the delta is minimal</p>

<figure style="width: 50%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-25/top.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 120%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
</figure>

<p><br /></p>

<p>This was all I could finish today; I started at 3:00 in the afternoon, and I ended at 10:00–a couple of hours after my shift ended.</p>

<p>Hopefully future updates aren’t as jam-packed as this; I was trying to fit in a lot of work that I had missed due to COVID.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="art" /><category term="woodworking" /><category term="guitar" /><category term="makerspace" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Home VPN, pt. 1: A Basic Setup</title><link href="/blog/vpn1.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Home VPN, pt. 1: A Basic Setup" /><published>2022-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-19T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/vpn1</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/vpn1.html"><![CDATA[<p>So right before I left for my trip to Florida I realized that there was no way to access my
home network remotely. This was a bit of a sitch, so now that I’m back, I’m finally going to make one.</p>

<p>This can be done in two ways, and I’m thinking of doing the former:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Create a jail/container on my NAS machine, host it there</li>
  <li>Set up another device and have it on bare metal</li>
</ul>

<p>While writing this, I tried doing all of this via a TrueNAS jail, but jails were missing features that I needed
for configuring and running a VPN. Luckily, I have a bunch of laptops laying around that I can install
OpenBSD on.</p>

<figure style="width: 100%;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-19/laptop.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 75%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">An old ACER Aspire that I installed OpenBSD 7.1 onto</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>I basically followed <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=szGsh5J9bzY">Mental Outlaw’s guide</a> on hosting a 
WireGuard VPN on OpenBSD, but the steps are as follows:</p>

<h4 id="vpn-server">VPN Server</h4>
<ol>
  <li>
    <p>I installed OpenBSD on my laptop, gave it a static IP, etc. I don’t believe having the IP be
dynamic would actually cause any issues, but it would be easier to configure on a static IP.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Allow ip forwarding. This needs to be put in <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/etc/sysctl.conf</code> for it to be persistent across reboots, apparently.
    <div class="language-conf highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> <span class="n">net</span>.<span class="n">inet</span>.<span class="n">ip</span>.<span class="n">forwarding</span>=<span class="m">1</span>
 <span class="n">machdep</span>.<span class="n">lidswitch</span>=<span class="m">0</span> <span class="c"># Needed to disable suspend on lid close
</span></code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>Install WireGuard and generate a keypair. Luckily, WireGuard has utilities for generating keys.
    <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> # wg genkey &gt; private.key
 # wg pubkey &lt; private.key &gt; public.key
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>Configure WireGuard. WireGuard doesn’t have a default config, but this should be enough to get it started.
    <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> [Interface]
 ListenPort = ******
 PrivateKey = ******************************************** # Server private key
    
 [Peer]
 PublicKey = ******************************************** # Client public key
 AllowedIPs = ***.***.***.***/**
 PersistentKeepalive = ***
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>Configure pf/firewall. I think I only need to add the following 3 lines:
    <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> pass in on wg0
 pass in inet proto udp from any to any port ***** # This port is the same as the listen port
 pass out on egress inet from (wg0:network) nat-to (bge:0)
</code></pre></div>    </div>
    <p>In the video, he’s using a Vultr VPS, which seems to have <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">vio0</code> as the default interface.
From my <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">ifconfig</code>, I believe that my device is <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">bge0</code>.</p>
  </li>
  <li>Configure the VPN ip settings. This is put into <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">/etc/hostname.wg0</code>.
    <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> inet xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx xxx.xxx.xxx.xxx NONE # ip addr and netmask
 up
 !/usr/local/bin/wg setconf wg0 /etc/wireguard/wg0.conf
</code></pre></div>    </div>
    <p>From here, I can simply start up the <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">wg0</code> device with</p>
    <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> # sh /etc/netstart wg0
</code></pre></div>    </div>
    <p>and it should start accepting connections to the VPN.</p>
  </li>
</ol>

<h4 id="vpn-client">VPN Client</h4>
<p>Configuration for the client is about the same, but I configured via <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">systemd-networkd</code>, so I used networkd-unit files.</p>
<ol>
  <li>Generate wireguard keypar.</li>
  <li>Created the WireGuard net device. The configuration is basically the same, just an added <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">NetDev</code> header. 
<code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Interface</code> info now goes under <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">WireGuard</code> and <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">Peer</code> info now goes under <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">WireGuardPeer</code>.
    <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> [NetDev]
 Name=wg0
 type=wireguard
 Description=WireGuard tunnel
    
 [WireGuard]
 PrivateKey=******************************************** # Client private key

 [WireGuardPeer]
 PublicKey=******************************************** # Server public key
 Endpoint=***.***.***.***:****** # Server public IP and wireguard listening port
 AllowedIPs=***.***.***.***/*** # Allowed IPs and netmasks, you can use wildcards
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
  <li>Added the associated network configuration.
    <div class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code> [Match]
 Name=wg0
    
 [Network]
 Address=***.***.***.***/***
</code></pre></div>    </div>
  </li>
</ol>

<p>Now I can just reload <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">systemd-networkd</code> and it should connect. I can successfully ping to the VPN server, but I can’t route the internet through it. I’ll have to figure out that another time.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="network" /><category term="computers" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[So right before I left for my trip to Florida I realized that there was no way to access my home network remotely. This was a bit of a sitch, so now that I’m back, I’m finally going to make one.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">A Needed Reflection</title><link href="/blog/reflection.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Needed Reflection" /><published>2022-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/reflection</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/reflection.html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve neglected this website quite a bit, admittedly. Rather, I haven’t had a need or want to use it until recently. With that, I have been feeling like I want to do something with this. Maybe start taking the whole blogging thing seriously, start documenting my life and projects, I’m not sure.</p>

<p>First thing’s first: to make a house a home. This site was made back when I was a budding CS student. Unfortunately with time, my style and aesthetics have changed, so this site is gonna need some work. I’ve been picking out new fonts, and brainstorming some new layouts, so expect this site to go through some growing pains. Hopefully at the end, I can feel like this site is worth being on.</p>

<figure style="width: 250px;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-10/strat.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 120%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">A stratocaster body I've been working on</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>Second: a catch-up on what I’ve been doing. I’ve been fixated on building guitars, so a lot of my time has been devoted to developing machining strategies, learning CAD, making design files, etc. I do have more programming things I want to do, and have a project in the background that me and my friend have been in talks about, but that’s going to be at a later date.</p>

<p>Another thing: I have finally gotten a job offer. I’m going to be a part of the corporate machine in no time, so while I am still working heavily at the Rutgers Makerspace, I will soon have to say goodbye to that era of my life. A bittersweet sentiment, but a needed one as I am beginning to grow out of the job (and its sutiations, but that’s a story for another time).</p>

<p><br />
<br />
<br />
<br /></p>

<p>Finally, what is left: lots of projects that I want to work on, mainly artistic, but may also include some technical things. I want to explore a lot of ideas and thoughts I have in my head, and alot of new mediums that I haven’t tried yet. Writing is one, and I will definitely get into it more as I go on in these next couple of weeks. There may even be a name for this artistic endeavor, but only time will tell if that will come to fruition; after all, I’ve never been the type to follow through with my projects.</p>

<p>That’s all for now.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve neglected this website quite a bit, admittedly. Rather, I haven’t had a need or want to use it until recently. With that, I have been feeling like I want to do something with this. Maybe start taking the whole blogging thing seriously, start documenting my life and projects, I’m not sure.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Recording on a Budget</title><link href="/blog/recording_budget.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recording on a Budget" /><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/recording_budget</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/recording_budget.html"><![CDATA[<p>This guide will serve to break down various considerations on audio recording for those that
lack the resources, space, or time to create a proper audio recording setting. As the topic
of recording as a whole is very large, the aim of this guide will be to set up an isolation
booth for single-person recording. This will be good for most applications, such as vocals,
simple instruments, and foley (SFX recordings).</p>

<h2 id="table-of-contents">TABLE OF CONTENTS</h2>
<ol>
  <li><a href="#budget">BUDGET</a></li>
  <li><a href="#hardware">HARDWARE</a></li>
  <li><a href="#acoustics">ACOUSTICS</a></li>
  <li><a href="#interference">INTERFERENCE</a></li>
  <li><a href="#example">EXAMPLE</a></li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion">CONCLUSION</a></li>
</ol>

<h2 id="budget">BUDGET</h2>
<p>One of the most important things to consider when designing anything is the budget you are willing to spend on it. 
This does not just mean how much money you are willing to spend on this project, 
but also <em>how much you want to spend on each aspect of it</em>. 
A good breakdown of a budget is as follows:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Actual recording hardware (Interface, Mic)</li>
  <li>Acoustic material (acoustic foam pads, reflectors, etc.)</li>
  <li>DIY materials (hardware + tools you would use for mounting or building DIY acoustic solutions)</li>
</ul>

<p>Depending on what you already have on you, what your space is like, among many other things, will change how you break 
down your budget between these three aspects. For this budget, a good start is 75-20-5. 
The following sections will provide more explanation on how this breakdown was derived.</p>

<h1 id="hardware">HARDWARE</h1>
<p>You can’t polish a turd. As such, your audio recordings will only be as clear and high-resolution as the hardware you use to record that stuff. 
However, that doesn’t necessarily mean that you need to spend millions of dollars to get decent sounding audio. 
Many times it just requires doing good research on the hardware that you need to get so you get the best bang-for-buck.</p>

<figure style="width: 20%;" class="md-figure md-figure--left">
    <div style="background: url('https://yourfreesounds.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/cardioid_pattern_graphics_wMic.png') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 20%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">Cardiod Pickup Pattern <br /><i>source: yourfreesounds.com</i></figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>For this project, we only need an audio interface and a microphone. Most understand that a good microphone will pick up sound better, 
but there are so many other considerations such as pickup patterns, diaphragm types, etc. For an iso booth, we will get a good XLR cardioid microphone. 
XLR is just a 3-prong connector that most interfaces use, and cardioid describes the pickup pattern, 
i.e.: where around the microphone will it pick up sound. A cardioid pattern picks up only around the front, and somewhat around the sides. This will be good to eliminate the cost for acoustic padding.</p>

<p><br />
<br />
<br />
<br />
<br />
<br />
<br /></p>

<figure style="width: 20%;" class="md-figure md-figure--right">
    <div style="background: url('https://external-content.duckduckgo.com/iu/?u=https%3A%2F%2Fmedia.sweetwater.com%2Fimages%2Fitems%2F750%2FUM2usb-large.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 50%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">Behringer UM2 Audio Interface <br /><i>source: Sweetwater</i></figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>Audio interfaces connect your audio devices to your computer. They also provide an audio-digital converter that is separate from your computer, which eliminates alot of electrical noise.
Audio interfaces at a low price point are all about the same, so just aim for a reputable company that makes good audio equipment. 
For instance, a Behringer UM2 is a good interface at just $30.</p>

<p><br />
<br />
<br />
<br />
<br />
<br /></p>

<p>Gear is far and plenty to come by, but consider these things when buying your recording hardware:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Buy used; there are many people out there reselling the gear you may be looking for for well under its original price.</li>
  <li>Look at reviews; look more at the negative reviews and see if you see any common reviews about the hardware or the (re)seller. 
Does it fail after a couple of months? Is the seller unreliable? Repeating reviews will tend to hold true.</li>
  <li>Weigh your options; most gear will have pros and cons at any price point. It is up to you to decide what you can compromise on and what you can’t sway on.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="acoustics">ACOUSTICS</h2>
<p>Listen to these two sounds and compare them.</p>
<audio src="/assets/2021-11-04/test1.wav" controls="" preload=""></audio>
<audio src="/assets/2021-11-04/test2.wav" controls="" preload=""></audio>

<p><br /></p>

<p>If you notice, one has a noticeable “flutter” or “shimmer” in the background when I clap.
The other, less background noise in general.</p>

<p>This effect is known as <strong>reverb</strong>, and it is the main enemy of an isolation room. 
Reverb is the reflection of sound from the walls of the room. With recording, 
especially loud noises and high gain, you may pick up the reverb from your sounds.
To eliminate reverb, you effectively need to redirect reflections, diffuse them, or absorb the
sound waves altogether.</p>

<p>Before we look at what we need to do to fix our reverb, we need to take a couple of considerations.
First you need to consider the room you are using; any furniture that is going to be in there will help 
reduce the severity of the reverb. Even hard furniture such as dressers and shelves can redirect the 
soundwaves in a way that your microphone won’t pick up. Second, you should consider the pickup pattern 
that your microphone has. Since we have gone with a cardioid pickup pattern, <em>we can completely ignore 
any reflections behind the microphone</em>, as it will not be picked up by the mic. 
Instead, we can focus on the reflections happening in front of the microphone and to the sides of the microphone.</p>

<p>With those considerations, we now need to think about how to rid of any relevant reflections in the room.
With enough money, space, and freedom, we could just pad the entire surface area of the room. However, you most likely do not
have that luxury. Instead, here are a couple of options that you can consider:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Fill your room with fabrics; most soft fabrics will dampen sound, so carpets, towels, etc. will all help
reduce sound reflections. One particular item that is super effective and very accessible is drapery, especially
large, pleated and layered curtains. These can diffuse sound very effectively.</li>
  <li>Reposition your recording devices; If you can, move your recording and audio devices as far away from other sound
sources or hard walls as you can. Positioning your audio things off-axis from walls (i.e.: not parallel) can also
help reduce direct reflections.</li>
  <li>Angle your furniture; something that you may not consider is how your furniture plays into reflections. Angling your
furniture in a way that can send reflections to the sides or to the back of the recording area can help reduce reverbs
that are picked up.</li>
  <li>Build DIY acoustic panels; you can do this using leftover rockwool, sheep wool, or some other type of insulation.
A good place to start is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dmHFbygUtO4">this video</a> by Kobi McCoull II. You
can modify this idea to fit your needs, but generally the DIY route will require some research to make efficient acoustic panels.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="interference">INTERFERENCE</h2>
<p>Any active sound source can act as interference: People, other speakers, etc. can all act as interference to the sound
that is picked up. However, did you know that even electrical devices can act as interference? Microphones can actually
pick up certain frequencies as low hum, depending on the size and distance of the electrical device. For instance, 
most fluorescent light fixtures create a low 60hz hum that microphones will easily pick up. Similarly, even
small components in computers and other circuits can create noises that your microphone or even your audio interface
can pick up.</p>

<p>This is why a standalone audio interface is a good buy for this project; your computer has an onboard interface, but since
it is inside your computer, it can also take in the sounds brought by electrical interference.</p>

<p>There are many other things you can do to minimize interference (at least the interference <em>you</em> can control):</p>
<ul>
  <li>Use low-traffic areas; places such as far closets and attic spaces make great recording rooms since not many people move around
there. If you can manage to use a similar room for recording, it may be a good idea to do so.</li>
  <li>Move electronic devices away from your recording equipment; this should minimize electrical interference. Even having solid walls
between your devices and your electronic equipment can help.</li>
  <li>Use LED lights instead of fluorescent fixtures; if you can simply get a floor lamp and use a LED lightbulb, that will eliminate
hum that comes from flouorescent lights.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="example">EXAMPLE</h2>
<p>For a real-life example of what this information would look like applied, take my apartment room and gear for example.</p>

<figure style="width: 25%;" class="md-figure md-figure--right">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2021-11-04/room.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 50%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">Corners of my room</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>My recording hardware is a Marantz MPM-1000 cardiod microphone, paired with a Behringer UM2 audio interface.
My apartment room is a small room, with a full-size bed and a band shirt on the wall. 
It’s hardwood flooring, with some type of softwood walls, and other furniture and things that fill up the space.
Here are some examples of both vocal and instrumental recordings in this room:</p>

<audio src="/assets/2021-11-04/voice.mp3" controls="" preload=""></audio>
<audio src="/assets/2021-11-04/inst.mp3" controls="" preload=""></audio>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Without much addition to my room, the quality of the recordings are already very nice. However, as you can tell there is still
some reverb that gets through the mic, particularly where I clap and snap. There are many ways to solve this issue. Personally,
I would consider putting some type of acoustic panel above my bed to dampen the reflections that come from there. My ceiling is hard
to pad, but a way of doing it could be to hang something on some stands above my head.</p>

<p>In terms of hardware, the cost is about $70, $30 for my audio interface and $40 for my microphone.
In terms of dedicated acoustic paneling, the cost is another $20, which brings the total of this project to just under $100.</p>

<p>Depending on your needs as well as where/how you source your hardware you may be able to spend less.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">CONCLUSION</h2>

<p>I hope that this guide provides some information on how to go about spending your money and setting up your room
for recording audio. There are plenty of other sources online if you want more information on anything in specific
that was covered in this guide. Be sure to also visit forums if you need other opinions on choices regarding audio
considerations or recording hardware.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="music" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This guide will serve to break down various considerations on audio recording for those that lack the resources, space, or time to create a proper audio recording setting. As the topic of recording as a whole is very large, the aim of this guide will be to set up an isolation booth for single-person recording. This will be good for most applications, such as vocals, simple instruments, and foley (SFX recordings).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome</title><link href="/blog/welcome.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome" /><published>2020-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/welcome.html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my new blog! This isn’t much of a post since the content of this is more for my own testing.
However, I do want to address some things about this site in this post, just to kill two birds
with one stone.</p>

<p>First off, this site serves as not only my portfolio site for my projects (non-programming including), but
serves as a place where I can get some thoughts out onto a space. For me, it just gives my head some freedom
to rant/talk/teach/etc. Some fun things might come out of the fact that I have this freedom now:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Random lessons on fun programming things that I personally find fun/interesting</li>
  <li>My own life doings, especially whatever I’m doing at the makerspace</li>
  <li>Music</li>
  <li>Opportunites</li>
  <li>???</li>
  <li>yea</li>
</ul>

<p>Second, I will host all the info about my relevant programming projects on this website. Keyword here is
relevant–I definitely have more projects on my <a href="https://github.com/Endoman123">GitHub</a>, but I don’t feel
like it helps any context of me being here; either they were passion projects that fell out of love, or the
project was just something I posted more for testing. Either way, they aren’t things I feel like making a post
for. There may come a time where a project I wasn’t working on becomes relevant, obviously, but until that happens,
they probably won’t have a post.</p>

<p>Third, code is definitely going to be in some of these posts. This is what it’s going to look like fenced off
(this clip is from my project <a href="https://github.com/Endoman123/hold-my-coffee">Hold My Coffee</a>).</p>

<div class="language-java highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="cm">/**
 * Abstract class intended on creating actions that can be schedule with the boss.
 * This allows for better control over what the boss does/can do during certain stages
 * or events.
 *
 * @author Jared Tulayan
 */</span>
<span class="kd">public</span> <span class="kd">static</span> <span class="kd">abstract</span> <span class="kd">class</span> <span class="nc">Action</span> <span class="o">{</span>
    <span class="kd">public</span> <span class="kt">boolean</span> <span class="n">parallel</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kc">false</span><span class="o">;</span>
    <span class="cm">/**
        * Runs the task.
        *
        * @param boss the {@code Entity} that this task is scheduled for
        * @param deltaTime the amount of time passed since last frame
        * @return whether or not the task is finished
        */</span>
    <span class="kd">public</span> <span class="kd">abstract</span> <span class="kt">boolean</span> <span class="nf">act</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="nc">Entity</span> <span class="n">boss</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="kt">float</span> <span class="n">deltaTime</span><span class="o">);</span>
<span class="o">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>I will try to be as cognisant as possible to tag posts with the relevant tags so that people know what they don’t want to read.</p>

<p>That’s all for now, catch up soon.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to my new blog! This isn’t much of a post since the content of this is more for my own testing. However, I do want to address some things about this site in this post, just to kill two birds with one stone.]]></summary></entry></feed>