<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.1.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2022-07-15T14:20:36+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">Jared Tulayan</title><subtitle>Rutgers Computer Science student</subtitle><entry><title type="html">A Needed Reflection</title><link href="/blog/reflection.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="A Needed Reflection" /><published>2022-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2022-07-10T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/reflection</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/reflection.html"><![CDATA[<p>I’ve neglected this website quite a bit, admittedly. Rather, I haven’t had a need or want to use it until recently. With that, I have been feeling like I want to do something with this. Maybe start taking the whole blogging thing seriously, start documenting my life and projects, I’m not sure.</p>

<p>First thing’s first: to make a house a home. This site was made back when I was a budding CS student. Unfortunately with time, my style and aesthetics have changed, so this site is gonna need some work. I’ve been picking out new fonts, and brainstorming some new layouts, so expect this site to go through some growing pains. Hopefully at the end, I can feel like this site is worth being on.</p>

<figure style="width: 250px;" class="md-figure">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2022-07-10/strat.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 120%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">A stratocaster body I've been working on</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>Second: a catch-up on what I’ve been doing. I’ve been fixated on building guitars, so a lot of my time has been devoted to developing machining strategies, learning CAD, making design files, etc. I do have more programming things I want to do, and have a project in the background that me and my friend have been in talks about, but that’s going to be at a later date.</p>

<p>Another thing: I have finally gotten a job offer. I’m going to be a part of the corporate machine in no time, so while I am still working heavily at the Rutgers Makerspace, I will soon have to say goodbye to that era of my life. A bittersweet sentiment, but a needed one as I am beginning to grow out of the job (and its sutiations, but that’s a story for another time).</p>

<p><br />
<br />
<br />
<br /></p>

<p>Finally, what is left: lots of projects that I want to work on, mainly artistic, but may also include some technical things. I want to explore a lot of ideas and thoughts I have in my head, and alot of new mediums that I haven’t tried yet. Writing is one, and I will definitely get into it more as I go on in these next couple of weeks. There may even be a name for this artistic endeavor, but only time will tell if that will come to fruition; after all, I’ve never been the type to follow through with my projects.</p>

<p>That’s all for now.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[I’ve neglected this website quite a bit, admittedly. Rather, I haven’t had a need or want to use it until recently. With that, I have been feeling like I want to do something with this. Maybe start taking the whole blogging thing seriously, start documenting my life and projects, I’m not sure.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Recording on a Budget</title><link href="/blog/recording_budget.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Recording on a Budget" /><published>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2021-11-04T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/recording_budget</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/recording_budget.html"><![CDATA[<p>This guide will serve to break down various considerations on audio recording for those that
lack the resources, space, or time to create a proper audio recording setting. As the topic
of recording as a whole is very large, the aim of this guide will be to set up an isolation
booth for single-person recording. This will be good for most applications, such as vocals,
simple instruments, and foley (SFX recordings).</p>

<h2 id="table-of-contents">TABLE OF CONTENTS</h2>
<ol>
  <li><a href="#budget">BUDGET</a></li>
  <li><a href="#hardware">HARDWARE</a></li>
  <li><a href="#acoustics">ACOUSTICS</a></li>
  <li><a href="#interference">INTERFERENCE</a></li>
  <li><a href="#example">EXAMPLE</a></li>
  <li><a href="#conclusion">CONCLUSION</a></li>
</ol>

<h2 id="budget">BUDGET</h2>
<p>One of the most important things to consider when designing anything is the budget you are willing to spend on it. 
This does not just mean how much money you are willing to spend on this project, 
but also <em>how much you want to spend on each aspect of it</em>. 
A good breakdown of a budget is as follows:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Actual recording hardware (Interface, Mic)</li>
  <li>Acoustic material (acoustic foam pads, reflectors, etc.)</li>
  <li>DIY materials (hardware + tools you would use for mounting or building DIY acoustic solutions)</li>
</ul>

<p>Depending on what you already have on you, what your space is like, among many other things, will change how you break 
down your budget between these three aspects. For this budget, a good start is 75-20-5. 
The following sections will provide more explanation on how this breakdown was derived.</p>

<h1 id="hardware">HARDWARE</h1>
<p>You can’t polish a turd. As such, your audio recordings will only be as clear and high-resolution as the hardware you use to record that stuff. 
However, that doesn’t necessarily mean that you need to spend millions of dollars to get decent sounding audio. 
Many times it just requires doing good research on the hardware that you need to get so you get the best bang-for-buck.</p>

<figure style="width: 20%;" class="md-figure md-figure--left">
    <div style="background: url('https://yourfreesounds.com/wp-content/uploads/2020/08/cardioid_pattern_graphics_wMic.png') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 20%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">Cardiod Pickup Pattern <br /><i>source: yourfreesounds.com</i></figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>For this project, we only need an audio interface and a microphone. Most understand that a good microphone will pick up sound better, 
but there are so many other considerations such as pickup patterns, diaphragm types, etc. For an iso booth, we will get a good XLR cardioid microphone. 
XLR is just a 3-prong connector that most interfaces use, and cardioid describes the pickup pattern, 
i.e.: where around the microphone will it pick up sound. A cardioid pattern picks up only around the front, and somewhat around the sides. This will be good to eliminate the cost for acoustic padding.</p>

<p><br />
<br />
<br />
<br />
<br />
<br />
<br /></p>

<figure style="width: 20%;" class="md-figure md-figure--right">
    <div style="background: url('https://external-content.duckduckgo.com/iu/?u=https%3A%2F%2Fmedia.sweetwater.com%2Fimages%2Fitems%2F750%2FUM2usb-large.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 50%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">Behringer UM2 Audio Interface <br /><i>source: Sweetwater</i></figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>Audio interfaces connect your audio devices to your computer. They also provide an audio-digital converter that is separate from your computer, which eliminates alot of electrical noise.
Audio interfaces at a low price point are all about the same, so just aim for a reputable company that makes good audio equipment. 
For instance, a Behringer UM2 is a good interface at just $30.</p>

<p><br />
<br />
<br />
<br />
<br />
<br /></p>

<p>Gear is far and plenty to come by, but consider these things when buying your recording hardware:</p>
<ul>
  <li>Buy used; there are many people out there reselling the gear you may be looking for for well under its original price.</li>
  <li>Look at reviews; look more at the negative reviews and see if you see any common reviews about the hardware or the (re)seller. 
Does it fail after a couple of months? Is the seller unreliable? Repeating reviews will tend to hold true.</li>
  <li>Weigh your options; most gear will have pros and cons at any price point. It is up to you to decide what you can compromise on and what you can’t sway on.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="acoustics">ACOUSTICS</h2>
<p>Listen to these two sounds and compare them.</p>
<audio src="/assets/2021-11-04/test1.wav" controls="" preload=""></audio>
<audio src="/assets/2021-11-04/test2.wav" controls="" preload=""></audio>

<p><br /></p>

<p>If you notice, one has a noticeable “flutter” or “shimmer” in the background when I clap.
The other, less background noise in general.</p>

<p>This effect is known as <strong>reverb</strong>, and it is the main enemy of an isolation room. 
Reverb is the reflection of sound from the walls of the room. With recording, 
especially loud noises and high gain, you may pick up the reverb from your sounds.
To eliminate reverb, you effectively need to redirect reflections, diffuse them, or absorb the
sound waves altogether.</p>

<p>Before we look at what we need to do to fix our reverb, we need to take a couple of considerations.
First you need to consider the room you are using; any furniture that is going to be in there will help 
reduce the severity of the reverb. Even hard furniture such as dressers and shelves can redirect the 
soundwaves in a way that your microphone won’t pick up. Second, you should consider the pickup pattern 
that your microphone has. Since we have gone with a cardioid pickup pattern, <em>we can completely ignore 
any reflections behind the microphone</em>, as it will not be picked up by the mic. 
Instead, we can focus on the reflections happening in front of the microphone and to the sides of the microphone.</p>

<p>With those considerations, we now need to think about how to rid of any relevant reflections in the room.
With enough money, space, and freedom, we could just pad the entire surface area of the room. However, you most likely do not
have that luxury. Instead, here are a couple of options that you can consider:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Fill your room with fabrics; most soft fabrics will dampen sound, so carpets, towels, etc. will all help
reduce sound reflections. One particular item that is super effective and very accessible is drapery, especially
large, pleated and layered curtains. These can diffuse sound very effectively.</li>
  <li>Reposition your recording devices; If you can, move your recording and audio devices as far away from other sound
sources or hard walls as you can. Positioning your audio things off-axis from walls (i.e.: not parallel) can also
help reduce direct reflections.</li>
  <li>Angle your furniture; something that you may not consider is how your furniture plays into reflections. Angling your
furniture in a way that can send reflections to the sides or to the back of the recording area can help reduce reverbs
that are picked up.</li>
  <li>Build DIY acoustic panels; you can do this using leftover rockwool, sheep wool, or some other type of insulation.
A good place to start is <a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=dmHFbygUtO4">this video</a> by Kobi McCoull II. You
can modify this idea to fit your needs, but generally the DIY route will require some research to make efficient acoustic panels.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="interference">INTERFERENCE</h2>
<p>Any active sound source can act as interference: People, other speakers, etc. can all act as interference to the sound
that is picked up. However, did you know that even electrical devices can act as interference? Microphones can actually
pick up certain frequencies as low hum, depending on the size and distance of the electrical device. For instance, 
most fluorescent light fixtures create a low 60hz hum that microphones will easily pick up. Similarly, even
small components in computers and other circuits can create noises that your microphone or even your audio interface
can pick up.</p>

<p>This is why a standalone audio interface is a good buy for this project; your computer has an onboard interface, but since
it is inside your computer, it can also take in the sounds brought by electrical interference.</p>

<p>There are many other things you can do to minimize interference (at least the interference <em>you</em> can control):</p>
<ul>
  <li>Use low-traffic areas; places such as far closets and attic spaces make great recording rooms since not many people move around
there. If you can manage to use a similar room for recording, it may be a good idea to do so.</li>
  <li>Move electronic devices away from your recording equipment; this should minimize electrical interference. Even having solid walls
between your devices and your electronic equipment can help.</li>
  <li>Use LED lights instead of fluorescent fixtures; if you can simply get a floor lamp and use a LED lightbulb, that will eliminate
hum that comes from flouorescent lights.</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="example">EXAMPLE</h2>
<p>For a real-life example of what this information would look like applied, take my apartment room and gear for example.</p>

<figure style="width: 25%;" class="md-figure md-figure--right">
    <div style="background: url('/assets/2021-11-04/room.jpg') center; background-size: cover; width: 100%; padding-bottom: 50%;" class="md-figure__image"></div>
    
        <figcaption class="md-figure__caption p-3">Corners of my room</figcaption>
    
</figure>

<p>My recording hardware is a Marantz MPM-1000 cardiod microphone, paired with a Behringer UM2 audio interface.
My apartment room is a small room, with a full-size bed and a band shirt on the wall. 
It’s hardwood flooring, with some type of softwood walls, and other furniture and things that fill up the space.
Here are some examples of both vocal and instrumental recordings in this room:</p>

<audio src="/assets/2021-11-04/voice.mp3" controls="" preload=""></audio>
<audio src="/assets/2021-11-04/inst.mp3" controls="" preload=""></audio>

<p><br /></p>

<p>Without much addition to my room, the quality of the recordings are already very nice. However, as you can tell there is still
some reverb that gets through the mic, particularly where I clap and snap. There are many ways to solve this issue. Personally,
I would consider putting some type of acoustic panel above my bed to dampen the reflections that come from there. My ceiling is hard
to pad, but a way of doing it could be to hang something on some stands above my head.</p>

<p>In terms of hardware, the cost is about $70, $30 for my audio interface and $40 for my microphone.
In terms of dedicated acoustic paneling, the cost is another $20, which brings the total of this project to just under $100.</p>

<p>Depending on your needs as well as where/how you source your hardware you may be able to spend less.</p>

<h2 id="conclusion">CONCLUSION</h2>

<p>I hope that this guide provides some information on how to go about spending your money and setting up your room
for recording audio. There are plenty of other sources online if you want more information on anything in specific
that was covered in this guide. Be sure to also visit forums if you need other opinions on choices regarding audio
considerations or recording hardware.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="music" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[This guide will serve to break down various considerations on audio recording for those that lack the resources, space, or time to create a proper audio recording setting. As the topic of recording as a whole is very large, the aim of this guide will be to set up an isolation booth for single-person recording. This will be good for most applications, such as vocals, simple instruments, and foley (SFX recordings).]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Welcome</title><link href="/blog/welcome.html" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Welcome" /><published>2020-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2020-07-01T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/blog/welcome</id><content type="html" xml:base="/blog/welcome.html"><![CDATA[<p>Welcome to my new blog! This isn’t much of a post since the content of this is more for my own testing.
However, I do want to address some things about this site in this post, just to kill two birds
with one stone.</p>

<p>First off, this site serves as not only my portfolio site for my projects (non-programming including), but
serves as a place where I can get some thoughts out onto a space. For me, it just gives my head some freedom
to rant/talk/teach/etc. Some fun things might come out of the fact that I have this freedom now:</p>

<ul>
  <li>Random lessons on fun programming things that I personally find fun/interesting</li>
  <li>My own life doings, especially whatever I’m doing at the makerspace</li>
  <li>Music</li>
  <li>Opportunites</li>
  <li>???</li>
  <li>yea</li>
</ul>

<p>Second, I will host all the info about my relevant programming projects on this website. Keyword here is
relevant–I definitely have more projects on my <a href="https://github.com/Endoman123">GitHub</a>, but I don’t feel
like it helps any context of me being here; either they were passion projects that fell out of love, or the
project was just something I posted more for testing. Either way, they aren’t things I feel like making a post
for. There may come a time where a project I wasn’t working on becomes relevant, obviously, but until that happens,
they probably won’t have a post.</p>

<p>Third, code is definitely going to be in some of these posts. This is what it’s going to look like fenced off
(this clip is from my project <a href="https://github.com/Endoman123/hold-my-coffee">Hold My Coffee</a>).</p>

<div class="language-java highlighter-rouge"><div class="highlight"><pre class="highlight"><code><span class="cm">/**
 * Abstract class intended on creating actions that can be schedule with the boss.
 * This allows for better control over what the boss does/can do during certain stages
 * or events.
 *
 * @author Jared Tulayan
 */</span>
<span class="kd">public</span> <span class="kd">static</span> <span class="kd">abstract</span> <span class="kd">class</span> <span class="nc">Action</span> <span class="o">{</span>
    <span class="kd">public</span> <span class="kt">boolean</span> <span class="n">parallel</span> <span class="o">=</span> <span class="kc">false</span><span class="o">;</span>
    <span class="cm">/**
        * Runs the task.
        *
        * @param boss the {@code Entity} that this task is scheduled for
        * @param deltaTime the amount of time passed since last frame
        * @return whether or not the task is finished
        */</span>
    <span class="kd">public</span> <span class="kd">abstract</span> <span class="kt">boolean</span> <span class="nf">act</span><span class="o">(</span><span class="nc">Entity</span> <span class="n">boss</span><span class="o">,</span> <span class="kt">float</span> <span class="n">deltaTime</span><span class="o">);</span>
<span class="o">}</span>
</code></pre></div></div>

<p>I will try to be as cognisant as possible to tag posts with the relevant tags so that people know what they don’t want to read.</p>

<p>That’s all for now, catch up soon.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><category term="personal" /><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Welcome to my new blog! This isn’t much of a post since the content of this is more for my own testing. However, I do want to address some things about this site in this post, just to kill two birds with one stone.]]></summary></entry></feed>